{"tossups": [{"question": "<b>A drunken Vyacheslav [vee-EH-cheh-slahf] Molotov asked this man, \u201cNow that soldiers have become statesmen in America, are the troops goose-stepping?\u201d This man was succeeded by Dean Acheson (+) in the first of his two Cabinet posts. The first person to be promoted to five-star general, this leader gave a June 1947 address at Harvard that was downplayed in American media but shared widely in (*)</b> Europe. For the points, name this American statesman who, as Secretary of State under Harry Truman, organized the European Recovery Program for Western Europe in a namesake 1948 \u201cPlan.\u201d", "answer": "George<b> Marshall</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Jasper Griffin claimed that this poet invented a brother to use as a foil for himself in one of his didactic poems. According to legend, this poet won a bronze stool for defeating Homer in a poetry contest, because his poems were less violent. One work by this poet includes (+) agricultural advice for his brother Perses. That poem by this author contains</b> <b>the oldest extant version of the ages of mankind: Gold, silver, bronze, heroic, (*)</b> and iron. For the points, name this ancient Greek poet, the author of the<em> Works and Days</em> and the<em> Theogony</em>.", "answer": "<b> Hesiod</b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Poetry"}, {"question": "<b>Ukawsaw Gronniosaw published the first of these works in England. In a work in this genre, the protagonist, Linda Brent, gives birth to Ellen and Benny after sleeping with Mr.</b> <b>Sands to avoid being raped by Dr. Flint. In a work in this genre, Mr. (+)</b> <b>Covey tries to</b> <b>\u201cbreak\u201d the protagonist, who later flees to New Bedford. That protagonist is taught how to read by Sophia, the daughter of the oppressive Mr. (*) </b> Hugh Auld. For the points, name this genre that includes the memoirs of Harriet Jacobs and Frederick Douglass, who recounted their experiences in captivity.", "answer": "<b> Slave narrative</b>s", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "<b>Insurgents in this territory shot down the German plane,</b><em><b> Polar 3</b></em><b>, on its way back from the South Pole. It\u2019s not Tunisia, but Noam Chomsky argued that the Gdeim Izik protest</b> <b>camp in this territory was the start of the Arab (+)</b> <b>Spring. Val\u00b4ery Giscard d\u2019Estaing</b> <b>ordered an airstrike on this territory in Operation Lamantin after French hostages were taken. 350,000 citizens occupied this territory in 1975 during the Green March, lessening Spanish influence. The POLISARIO (*)</b> Front declared the independence of the Sahrawi Republic in this territory. For the points, name this disputed territory bordering Morocco.", "answer": "<b> Western Sahara</b> (accept<b> Sahrawi Arab Democratic Republic</b> or<b> SADR</b> before mentioned, do not accept or prompt on \u201cMorocco\u201d)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This term is used for a government against which an opponent wrote the song \u201cDying of Hunger, Dying of Cold\u201d after being imprisoned for running the newspaper</b><em><b> Tribune of</b></em> <em><b>the People</b></em><b>. A subculture under this government was known as the \u201cincredibles\u201d (+)</b> <b>and</b> <b>wore green jackets, thick glasses, and styled their hair like dog ears. Gracchus Babeuf was executed for attempting to overthrow this government in the Conspiracy of the Equals. Paul (*) </b> Barras declared himself the leader of this government after the Battle of 13 Vendemaire. For the points, name this French Revolutionary government ended by Napoleon\u2019s coup.", "answer": "French<b> Directory</b> (accept<b> Directorate</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>To avoid arrest, this man assumed the pseudonym \u201cBarry Freed\u201d and wrote as a travel columnist for</b><em><b> Crawdaddy!</b></em><b> magazine. This man threw dollars onto the floor of the New York Stock Exchange to protest corporate greed. Pete Townshend (+) hit this man with a guitar after he ran up on stage during a performance by The Who to protest the imprisonment of White Panther Party founder John Sinclair. This man attempted to levitate the Pentagon in 1967 with Jerry Rubin (*) </b> and nominated \u201cPigasus\u201d for president at the 1968 DNC. For the points, name this counterculture activist and member of the Chicago Seven.", "answer": "Abbie<b> Hoffman</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>A year after this treaty was signed, Pieter Corbeels led a Peasants\u2019 War in a region of Flanders that had changed hands. This treaty was signed at Betrando Del Torre\u2019s house after one side\u2019s commander rested at Ludovico Manin\u2019s villa. The Cisalpine and Ligurian</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>Republics were recognized in this treaty, which followed the Armistice of Leoben</b> <b>and ended over a millennium of independence for Venice. As part of this Philipp von Cobenzl-negotiated treaty, the Austrian side released the Marquis (*) </b> de Lafayette from prison. For the points, name this 1797 treaty which Napoleon signed after a victorious campaign in Italy.", "answer": "Treaty of<b> Campo Formio</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This composer depicted the mocking of Christ in the movement \u201cEt viri, qui tenebant illum.\u201d In 1980, this man was commissioned by</b><em><b> Solidarno\u00b4s\u00b4c</b></em><b> to compose a piece accompanying the unveiling of a statue in memory of those killed in 1970 anti-government riots at the (+) Gdansk shipyards. This composer of the</b><em><b> Polish Requiem</b></em><b> is known for a piece for fifty-two strings including massive tone clusters dedicated to those (*)</b> killed by an atomic bomb. For the points, name this composer of<em> St. Luke\u2019s Passion</em> and<em> Threnody for the Victims of Hiroshima</em>.", "answer": "Krzysztof<b> Penderecki</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This politician passed the</b><em><b> Lex Acilia</b></em><b> to put the</b><em><b> equites</b></em><b> in charge of extortion trials, and he attempted to extend \u201cLatin Rights\u201d to all Italian allies. This man was implicated in the death of his brother-in-law, Scipio Aemilianus. (+) This man\u2019s political career began while serving in a land-commission established by his brother that was fiercely opposed by the Senatorial class. This man committed suicide in 121 BC to avoid a (*) </b> pro-Senate mob. For the points, name this younger of a pair of Romans who attempted to redistribute land to poor citizens, the brother of Tiberius.", "answer": "<b> Gaius Gracchus</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s \u201cRaiders\u201d may have been the subject of a completely fabricated skirmish at Ward\u2019s Tavern to boost the reputation of Portuguese-born patriot Peter Francisco. While attempting to negotiate a truce with Abraham Buford, this man\u2019s (+) horse was shot from under him, prompting his troops to commit the Waxhaw Massacre in South Carolina and earning him the nickname \u201cThe Butcher.\u201d Three lines by the Broad River were employed by Daniel Morgan to defeat this commander of the (*)</b> British Legion. For the points, name this British general who was defeated at the Battle of Cowpens.", "answer": "Banastre<b> Tarleton</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This person\u2019s name was adopted by Siwanoy chief Wampage as their people cusomarily took the name of the most famous person they killed. This follower of John Cotton declared,\u201cYou have no power over my body\u201d to men such as Thomas Dudley, who opposed this person preaching Cotton\u2019s (+) \u201ccovenant of grace\u201d theology. After being put on trial during the Antinomian controversy, this person moved to the newly founded (*)</b> Portsmouth colony. For the points, name this woman who moved to Rhode Island after being expelled from the Massachusetts Bay Colony for unorthodox theological teachings.", "answer": "Anne<b> Hutchinson</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A musical work named for this event was arranged for trumpet by Jean-Baptiste Arban and was first popularized by Niccolo Paganini. In 1797, Francis II outlawed this event, which</b> <b>began in 1162 after the defeat of the Patriarch of Aquileia, (+)</b> <b>Ulrico di Treven. During</b> <b>this event, people often wear</b><em><b> bauta</b></em><b> and costumes inspired by French physician Charles de Lorme who invented the</b><em><b> medicao della peste</b></em><b>. This event returned in 1979 but was called off in February (*) </b> 2020 due to COVID-19. For the points, name this annual festival in which attendees celebrate Mardi Gras by the Grand Canal while wearing masks.", "answer": "<b> Carnival</b> of<b> Venice</b> (accept<b> Carnevale</b> di<b> Venezia</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man helped found the Emanuel African Methodist Episcopal Church, the oldest AME church in the US South, which was burned by an angry crowd. Governor Thomas Bennett objected to the secret court proceedings surrounding this man, arguing that he</b> <b>deserved the right of (+)</b> <b>habeas corpus as he was a free man. This man had purchased</b> <b>his freedom with lottery winnings and had previously been known as Telemaque. George Wilson and Joe LaRoche (*)</b> exposed this man\u2019s Bastille Day plans. For the points, name this leader of \u201cThe Rising,\u201d a planned 1822 slave revolt in Charleston.", "answer": "Denmark<b> Vesey</b> (accept<b> Telemaque</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>A Nicaraguan group named for the use of this specific product used it to protest the arrest of Marl\u00b4en Chow at a 2018 anti-Ortega demonstration. A protester in Macedonia used this product to deface a police riot shield in 2015. Beginning in 1941, a variety of this</b> <b>product nicknamed (+)</b> <b>\u201cMontezuma\u201d was standard-issue for women in the U.S. Army.</b> <b>That product was designed by Elizabeth Arden, who distributed this product to Charlotte (*) </b> Perkins Gilman and other protesting suffragettes in the 1910s and 20s. For the points, name this specific product used in protests like Nicaragua\u2019s \u201cSoy Pico Rojo.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Red lipstick</b> (prompt on \u201cmakeup\u201d and other similar answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>A cartoon of this scandal by John Wilson Bengough shows a man saying, \u201cThese Hands are clean\u201d while his left hand reads, \u201cSend me another<u> $</u>10,000.\u201d John Abbott was asked for money in this scandal, which included a suspension of Parliament by Lord (+) Dufferin. During this scandal, George Norris stole incriminating letters and sold them to the Liberals. Hugh Allan wrote a letter to Americans saying he would be made head of the company that was central to this scandal. The first ministry of John (*) </b> Macdonald was rocked by, for the points, what 1870s political scandal involving a Canadian transcontinental railway?", "answer": "<b> Pacific</b> scandal", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This ruler built the Allgemeines Krankenhaus as part of his plan to centralize healthcare in a single hospital, though that only increased infection rates. Pope Pius VI paid a visit</b> <b>to this ruler after he dissolved hundreds of monasteries in his country. Vonckists (+)</b> <b>and</b> <b>Statists clashed in a revolt against this ruler that resulted in the creation of the United Belgian States. This ruler guaranteed private religious freedom with the Patent of Toleration and abolished (*)</b> serfdom in his country. For the points, name this enlightened despot who succeeded his mother Maria Theresa as Emperor of Austria.", "answer": "<b> Joseph II</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man helped lead an uprising in 1944 against the government of Jozef Tiso. While imprisoned, this man\u2019s appeals to the Communist leaders were ignored as (+) Antonin Novotny feared what he could do if released. This man led his nation through a period called \u201cNormalization\u201d after succeeding Alexander (*)</b> Dubcek in his most notable position. For the points, name this man who from 1975 to 1989 served as president of Czechoslovakia.", "answer": "<b> Mapuche</b> (accept<b> Araucanians</b> prior to \u201cArauco War,\u201d prompt on descriptions of indigenous people of Chile) (29) <b>This man was sentenced to life in Leopoldov Prison following a Stalinist purge of</b> <b>Communist Party leaders but was released after six years in 1960. This man helped lead an uprising in 1944 against the government of Jozef Tiso. While imprisoned, this man\u2019s appeals to the Communist leaders were ignored as (+) Antonin Novotny feared what he could do if released. This man led his nation through a period called \u201cNormalization\u201d after succeeding Alexander (*)</b> Dubcek in his most notable position. For the points, name this man who from 1975 to 1989 served as president of Czechoslovakia. ANSWER: Gust\u00b4av<b> Hus\u00b4ak</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This man fled his home country in 1795 but disliked American attachment to money. While living in Philadelphia, this man described George Washington as a \u201chigh-flying aristocrat.\u201d This man anonymously signed a 1791 pamphlet arguing on behalf of Catholics as (+) \u201cA Northern Whig.\u201d That distinguished this man from other Whigs from his country like Henry Grattan and Henry Flood who wanted Catholic emancipation without separation from England. This man was the leader of the Society of United Irishmen when it launched the Irish (*)</b> Rebellion of 1798. For the points, name this \u201cFather of Irish Republicanism.\u201d", "answer": "Theobald Wolfe<b> Tone</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This musician\u2019s recordings for Alfred Lion\u2019s Blue Note Records are collected in several albums titled</b><em><b> Genius of Modern Music, Volume 1</b></em><b>. Footage commissioned in 1967 by West German Public Television was used to create a Clint Eastwood-produced (+) documentary about this musician. Charlotte Zwerin directed that documentary about this musician, using Christian Blackwood\u2019s footage called the \u201cDead Sea Scrolls of Jazz,\u201d subtitled (*)</b> \u201cStraight, No Chaser.\u201d For the points, name this jazz pianist, the composer of the most recorded jazz standard in history, \u201cRound Midnight.\u201d", "answer": "Thelonious<b> Monk</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Jazz"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>One person with this first name suggested the deportations that became the Circassian Genocide. One ruler of this name married Marina Mniszek before Basil IV had him</b> <b>murdered. A prince of this name defeated the Golden (+)</b> <b>Horde near the Don River at</b> <b>Kulikovo Field in 1380. This was the first name of Alexander II\u2019s Minister of War, whose surname was Milyutin. The youngest son of Ivan the (*)</b> Terrible had this name, and he probably died during the regency of Boris Godunov. For the points, give this name claimed by many pretenders during the Time of Troubles.", "answer": "<b> Dmitry</b> (accept<b> Dmitry</b> Milyutin, accept<b> Dmitry</b> Ivanovich, accept<b> Dmitry</b> Donskoy, accept<b> Dmitry</b> of the Don, accept the False<b> Dmitry</b>s)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This man claimed that a nation that spends more on military defense than social uplift\u201cis approaching spiritual death.\u201d In a speech at Riverside Church, this man said the U.S. was \u201cthe greatest purveyor of (+) violence in the world today.\u201d This man lost the support of allies like Billy Graham after giving his \u201cBeyond Vietnam\u201d address against the war. In one speech, this man proclaimed, \u201cI\u2019m not fearing any man. (*)</b> Mine eyes have seen the glory of the coming of the Lord.\u201d For the points, name this civil rights leader who gave his best known speech on August 28, 1963 on the steps of the Lincoln Memorial.", "answer": "Martin Luther<b> King</b> Jr. (or<b> MLK</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 1865, Ulysses Grant was given an Italianate brick house in this state where his home is now a museum in the city of (*) </b>Galena. For the points, name this midwestern state where one can visit the tomb of Abraham Lincoln.", "answer": "<b> Illinois</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In response to this event, Thomas Pynchon wrote a</b><em><b> New York Times</b></em><b> op-ed titled \u201cA Journey Into the Mind of\u201d the neighborhood where this event took place. A 1972 music</b> <b>festival including a speech from Jesse Jackson (+)</b> <b>was marketed as \u201cbrothers and sisters</b> <b>turning on to being black\u201d and commemorated the 7th anniversary of this event. The McCone Report was commissioned by Governor Pat Brown (*)</b> to investigate this event, which began when Marquette Frye was arrested for drunk driving. Thirty-four people died during six days of unrest as part of, for the points, what 1965 race riot in Los Angeles?", "answer": "<b> Watts</b> Riots (accept<b> Watts</b> Rebellion,<b> Watts</b> Uprising, accept other synonyms for \u201cRiots\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This man helped the Teutonic Knights in a siege of Vilnius where he tried to convert captured Lithuanians at K\u00a8onigsberg. Edward of Norwich revealed a plot to kill this man, and Richard le Scrope led the Northern Uprising (+) against this man. Lord Bardolf aided an enemy of this man who killed this king\u2019s standard bearer, Walter Blount, before being killed at the Battle of Shrewsbury. Owen Glendower led a Welsh uprising against this man who faced the Epiphany (*) </b> Plot, an attempt to restore Richard II to the throne. Defeating his former ally, Henry \u201cHotspur\u201d Percy, for the points, name this first Lancastrian king.", "answer": "<b> Henry IV</b> Bolingbroke", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}